ILGWU. Local 226 records, 5780/132
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Local 226 records
1946-1973.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 226
5780/132
1 cubic feet
1 linear foot
Records
Contains records of Local 226, including agreements with area companies, as well as correspondence with those companies and union members. Also included are periodicals from several district councils in New England and Pennsylvania: Southern New England District News, Seamlines (Upstate New York and Vermont District), Garment Square Chronicle (Southern New England District), Needle News (Allentown-Reading District), and Needlepoint (Wilkes-Barre-Pittston-Nanticoke District).
5518302
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Local 226 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) was based in Springfield, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
Contains records of Local 226, including agreements with area companies, as well as correspondence with those companies and union members. Also included are periodicals from several district councils in New England and Pennsylvania: Southern New England District News, Seamlines (Upstate New York and Vermont District), Garment Square Chronicle (Southern New England District), Needle News (Allentown-Reading District), and Needlepoint (Wilkes-Barre-Pittston-Nanticoke District).
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 226
5518302
- Southern New England District News, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  October
- Aaron Dress Company, 1943-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Barton Tailoring Company, 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Sam J. Belsky, Incorporated, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Burnette Corporation, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Campus Girl, Incorporated, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cromwell Manufacturing Company, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Cromwell Mills, Incorporated, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Desley Fabrics Company, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Flair Fashions, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- M. Freed and Sons, Incorporated, 1944-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Glernap, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Huntington Fashions, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Julson Manufacturing Company, Incorporated, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Junior Miss Lingerie, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Ken Whitemore, Incorporated, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Kestral Corporation, 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- M. G. Kinser Company, 1938-1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Knit Goods Specialty Company, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Madelle Corporation, Incorporated, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Malone Knitting Company, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- National Transparent Plastics Company, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- New England Manufacturing Company, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Orange Garment Manufacturing Company, Incorporated, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Pioneer Valley Plastics Company, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Powdrell and Alexander, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Rainbow Girl Coat, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- I. L. Strick Company, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- S. G. Winer Company, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Trencher, Incorporated, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Victory Dress Company, 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Whitley Tailleurs, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- The William Carter Company, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Young and Trim Coat Company, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Seamlines, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  June 1959 - November 1961
- Education, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Garment Square Chronicle, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  December 1959 - June 1961
- Needle News, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  September 1960 - December 1961
- Needlepoint, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  February 1959 - August 1961